Give me some salt.
Mau di mana, Chef?
- Afternoon, Chef!
Sore, Chef.
You.
Hei.
Yes, Chef?
Iya, Chef.
- How many fingers is this? - Two, Chef.
- Ini berapa? - Dua.
- Two, right? - Yes, two.
- Dua, 'kan?
So, you're not fucking blind!
Berarti enggak buta, dong?
Then, what the hell is this?
Lo lihat ini apaan!
Clean this shit thoroughly!
Bersihin! Lap yang bener!
And this one too!
Ini juga, nih!
Yes, Chef.
Ya, Chef.
Change this one.
Kasih lagi, biar...
This one.
Biar sama yang ini.
What the hell is this?
Apa-apaan, sih, ini? Ha?
- Sorry, Chef! - Can't you do it right?
- Maaf, Chef. - Motong yang bener, dong!
- Yes, Chef! - Throw this one out!
- Siap, Chef. - Ulang...
Make it from scratch!
Ulang!
- And clean it beforehand! - Yes, Chef.
- Bersihin dulu yang di situ. - Siap.
Let me try.
Coba.
- Add this. - Yes, Chef.
- Tambahin. - Ya, Chef.
Hurry up!
Ayo, yang cepet!
The guests are waiting!
Tamu udah pada nunggu!
- Come on, hurry up! - Yes, Chef!
- Ayo, keseimbangannya! - Ya, Chef.
Is this the best you can do as the top graduates?
Katanya lulusan terbaik. Gimana, sih?
Come on, hurry up!
Ayo!
Uci. From Miss Dinda.
Uci, titipan Bu Dinda.
- Okay, Chef. - Okay.
Oke, Chef.
SHRIMP PASTE - GRADE A
TERASI UDANG KUALITAS A
Bring me the sauce, Chef!
Chef, saus mana, Chef?
Here it is, Chef.
Ini, Chef.
What the hell is that?
Saus apaan itu? Ha? Saus apaan?
Local fusion sauce that Miss Dinda requested, Chef.
Saus perpaduan lokal permintaan Bu Dinda, Chef.
- Using shrimp paste. - Shrimp paste?
- Pakai terasi. - Pakai terasi?
You idiot!
Goblok!
I prepared it for months and you put shrimp paste on?
Gue siapin berbulan-bulan, lo kasih terasi?
What the hell are you thinking?
Mikir apa lu? Ha?
Only perfection comes from this kitchen.
Cuma kesempurnaan yang lahir di dapur ini!
Don't you understand?
Ngerti, enggak, lo?
- Sorry, Chef! - This is not her fault, Chef.
- Sori, Chef. - Chef.
Do not interfere!
- Uci enggak salah. - Lo enggak usah ikut campur.
Dinda asked for an additional sauce
Dinda memang minta saus tambahan.
for the guests who prefer local dishes.
Buat tamu yang sukanya masakan lokal, Chef.
Try it, then.
Cobain.
Try it!
Coba!
Spit it out!
Lepeh.
You're my Sous-chef,
Lo sous-chef gue.
got it?
Ngerti, enggak?
Don't be a smartass and interfere with my business.
Enggak usah sotoy. Enggak usah sok ikut campur.
Chef.
Chef,
Now, I'd like to ask you.
gue tanya ama lo.
Who's your head chef? Me or Dinda?
Chef lo, gue, atau Dinda?
- Chef Ressa. - Who?
- Chef Ressa. - Apa?
- Now you know!
- Chef Ressa! - Pinter!
Take off your apron!
Lepas apron lo.
Now!
Buruan!
Put it down!
Taro.
Leave my kitchen!
Keluar dari dapur gue.
Now! And don't you dare to come back!
Buru! Enggak usah balik lu!
- Yes, Chef. - What a smarty-pants!
- Ya, Chef. - Sotoy banget jadi orang.
All-hands come here!
Semuanya! Ayo, ke sini semua!
Quickly!
Buruan!
Everybody listen!
Denger, ya, Semua.
For one last time,
Gue ingetin sekali lagi.
Maharasa only gives the guests
Maharasa hanya menjanjikan
véra Cucina Italiana, the real Italian taste.
vera cucina italiana.
- Understand? - Yes, Chef!
- Ngerti, enggak? - Ya, Chef.
Pasta is our speciality.
Spesialisasi kita itu pasta!
There's no shrimp paste, coriander, or anything like that!
Enggak ada tuh terasi-terasian, ketumbar. Apa, kek.
Tell them to go to a Wartega roadside stall
Yang mau bumbu lokal,
if they want to eat something local.
suruh makan di warteg!
- Understand? - Yes, Chef.
- Ngerti, enggak, lo? - Ya, Chef.
Freaking idiots!
Goblok lo semua!
Take five! Go away!
Jeda dulu! Cabut!
Ossobuco from Maharasa.
Ossobuco dari Maharasa.
Wow.
Wow.
Okay.
Oke.
Very delicious!
Enak sekali.
Amazing!
Luar biasa.
Hey.
Hei.
We're at a party.
Kita sedang berpesta.
Okay then, everybody hungry?
Baiklah. Kita lapar, oke?
Let's eat now!
Makan!
Magnificent.
Hebat!
Amazing food
Makanan lezat,
and extraordinary performance.
pertunjukan hebat.
You are truly...
Kamu memang
a genius!
benar-benar genius.
Thank you, Sir.
Terima kasih, Pak.
How can you make that pasta
Pasta itu bisa menjadi nikmat seperti itu.
so satisfying and flavourful?
Itu bagaimana? Bagaimana caranya?
We import the spices from Gragnano, Sir.
Jadi, kita memang menggunakan bumbu yang diimpor langsung dari Gragnano,
The city where my Papa was born.
kota kelahiran papa aku di Italia.
A city that is crazy about pasta.
Kota pasta.
That's right.
Ya.
Hi, Dad.
Pa.
Sorry, I'm late. The shooting went longer than we expected.
Sori telat. Syutingnya molor.
- Hi.
Hai.
My love!
Sayang.
You're late.
Kamu terlambat.
You didn't witness
Kamu tidak melihat
your boyfriend's magnificent performance.
hebatnya penampilan pacarmu.
He must've been amazing, right?
Keren banget, ya, pasti?
Then, you agree to invest in his restaurant in Italy?
Berarti Papa jadi, dong, buka restoran di Italia?
Alright.
Baik.
- Come to my house tomorrow. - Yes, Sir.
- Kalau gitu, besok malam, ya? - Ya.
I will be waiting for you at my house.
Aku tunggu di rumah.
Okay, Sir.
Siap, Pak.
- I'll see you tomorrow. - Bye-bye, Darling.
- Besok. - Dah, Sayang.
One more step and my dream will come true.
Satu langkah lagi, impian aku jadi kenyataan.
You're amazing.
Kamu hebat.
Because you're always here with me.
Karena kamu selalu bantuin aku.
Have you eaten?
Udah makan, belom?
Not yet. I'm famished.
Belom, nih. Laper.
Okay, sit down. I'll bring you some food.
Ya udah, duduk. Aku ambilin makanan.
PANGAN NUSANTARA PERKASA GROUP COMMERCIAL INVOICE
FAKTUR PENJUALAN
Excuse me, Sir.
Permisi, Pak.
Mr. Ressa is already here.
Mas Ressa sudah datang.
So,
Jadi,
I need to sign this document tonight, right?
ini berkas yang saya harus tanda tangani malam ini, ya?
Yes, Sir.
Iya, Pak.
This is for
Ini tentang
100 containers that will be shipped to the USA, right?
seratus kontainer ke Amerika, 'kan?
Yes, Sir.
Betul, Pak.
Okay.
Oke.
Excuse me, Sir.
Permisi, Pak.
Please come in, Mr. Ressa.
Silakan, Mas Ressa.
Mr. Broto.
Pak Broto.
Are all these authentic?
Ini semua asli, Pak?
All of these?
Ini?
Of course they are!
Asli.
Are you doubting me?
Kamu masih meragukan saya?
That is...
Kalo itu...
a photo of Dinda's brothers, right?
foto kakaknya Dinda, ya?
I thought I would only have two sons...
Tadinya, saya berpikir tuh cuma punya dua anak laki-laki.
even though I wanted a daughter.
Padahal aku ngebet, pengen punya anak perempuan.
But when I was 50 years old...
Ketika saya usia 50 tahun,
God finally answered my prayers.
ternyata doa saya dikabulkan.
Dinda was born.
Dinda lahir.
So...
Jadi...
I would like to ask you.
saya cuma mau nanya.
in love with...
kamu mencintai
my youngest child?
anak ragil saya?
Truly, Sir.
Sangat, Pak.
Then,
Kalo gitu,
All of this...
semua ini
is worth billions.
nilainya miliaran,
And I will give it...
dan akan saya wariskan
to Dinda.
kepada Dinda.
Including this one.
Termasuk ini.
Have a seat.
Silakan duduk.
I will give this to Dinda.
Ini juga saya akan wariskan kepada dia.
You have to learn it thoroughly.
Kamu harus pelajari ini baik-baik.
Mustika Rasa - The Taste of Flavour.
"Mustikarasa."
Mustika Rasa is full of...
Ya, Mustikarasa itu adalah
Indonesian authentic food recipes.
daftar makanan dari seluruh daerah di Nusantara.
The legacy of Soekarno.
Warisan Bung Karno.
There are 1000 recipes in here.
Di sini, yang diarsipkan baru 1.000.
There are 945 more, but it's still a mystery.
Yang 945 masih misteri.
1000?
Ada 1.000?
Yes.
Ya.
And you need to know, Ressa.
Dan kamu harus tau, Ressa.
Indonesia is very rich in natural resources.
Indonesia itu sangat kaya dengan kekayaan alam.
One of them is culinary.
Antara lain kuliner.
Culinary is like...
Kuliner itu
the art of persuasion through the tongue.
semacam seni meramu lidah.
That's why the founding fathers...
Makanya, Bapak Bangsa Indonesia...
thought that we could use culinary...
...berpikir bahwa kuliner ini bisa dijadikan
as our political tool.
alat politik bangsa.
Gastronomy diplomacy.
Diplomasi gastronomi.
Diplomacy through the stomach.
Diplomasi lewat perut.
What's wrong with you?
Kenapa kamu?
Ah, I see. So, Dinda is not lying.
Oh, ternyata, yang Dinda bilang itu benar?
You will feel queasy...
Akan mual perutmu
when we're talking about Indonesian food.
kalau bicara tentang makanan Indonesia.
So that's why...
Pantes,
when I asked Dinda to make a shrimp paste sauce...
aku pesan saus terasi pada Dinda,
it was nowhere to be seen.
enggak pernah datang.
I'm sorry, Sir.
Maaf, Pak.
I thought...
Tadinya, saya berpikir, ya,
you could use Mustika Rasa as reference.
bahwa Mustikarasa ini bisa jadi referensi.
But it's a pity that...
Tapi sayangnya...
our beloved Chef...
chef kita ini
is feeling nausea if we're talking about Indonesian food.
sakit perut kalau bicara tentang masakan Indonesia.
About the test food.
Tentang uji makanan itu...
You could just send me the sample...
Kamu kirimkan saja
on Monday morning and make a new menu...
Senin pagi, dan tambahkan menunya
from the references that I give you.
dengan apa yang aku sampaikan barusan.
If you're not sure...
Kalau kamu ragu,
then we should cancel...
ekspansi ke Italia
the expansion plan to Italy.
lebih baik kita batalkan.
That's the door.
Sekarang, pintuku terbuka.
Please...
Silakan
leave my office now.
kamu keluar dari kantor saya.
I'll deliver it on Monday, Sir.
Senin, Pak?
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
I feel bad about how I left things with your Dad.
Ya, tapi aku jadi enggak enak gitu ama papa kamu.
He's quite the nationalist.
Papa tuh emang nasionalis banget.
You are overthinking.
Kamu terlalu berlebihan memikirkannya.
Don't over think it.
Udah, enggak usah dipikirin.
Alright.
Ya udah.
You're the only one who can make me calm.
Emang cuma kamu yang bisa bikin aku tenang.
Dinda.
Oh, iya, Din. Aku...
I couldn't come tonight, is that alright?
malam ini enggak jadi ke sana. Enggak apa-apa, ya?
It's okay.
Enggak apa-apa.
Let's celebrate our anniversary tomorrow, okay?
Kita rayain hari jadi kita besok pagi?
Alright.
Iya, enggak apa-apa.
See you.
Dah.
Chef, can I have your authograph?
Chef, boleh minta tanda tanga, enggak?
Sure.
Boleh.
Are you going to surprise your girlfriend?
Mau kasih pacarnya kejutan, ya, Chef?
My soon-to-be wife.
Insyaallah calon istri.
Thank you, Chef.
Terima kasih, ya, Chef.
- Here it is. - All set?
- Ini, ya. - Udah semua, ya?
All set.
Sudah.
- Thank you. - Okay.
Makasih, ya.
You bastard!
Lo bangsat!
- You bastard! - Ressa!
Ressa.
Stop! Ressa, Alex, stop!
Stop! Ressa, Alex, stop!
Fuck you!
Anjing!
Ressa, Alex, stop!
Ressa, Alex, stop!
I can't believe it!
Tega lo, ya?
You're cheating on our anniversary.
Di hari jadi kita, lo bisa selingkuh!
- I... I... - She's mine now.
- Aku... - Dinda sekarang punya gue.
I didn't talk to you, you fucker!
Gue enggak ngomong ama lu, Anjing.
A self-proclaimed Chef,
Chef, katanya.
who can't even distinguish spices. Idiot!
Bumbu aja enggak bisa bedain. Goblok.
I never feel nauseous or throw up...
gue enggak pernah mual dan muntah
because of Indonesian food.
gara-gara makanan Indonesia.
How long are you going to hide your weakness?
Sampai kapan lo mau nutupin cacat lo?
Listen, Chef.
Sekarang gini, ya, Chef.
How can you create perfection from your kitchen...
Gimana caranya lo mau bikin kesempurnaan dapur
if you have a handicap?
kalo lo itu cacat,
And have a shit personality!
dan kelakukan lo bangsat?
Fuck you! Bastard!
- Anjing lo! - Bangsat!
Stop!
- Anjing, lo, ya. - Stop!
Stop! Stop!
Stop!
Stop! Enough!
Stop! Cukup!
Papa asked Alex to handle the new concept of Maharasa.
Papa mau Alex mengurus konsep Maharasa yang baru.
The localized one.
Yang lebih lokal.
The one that is more Indonesian.
Yang lebih Nusantara.
I'm sorry, Ressa.
Sori, Res.
and I respect it.
Dan aku menghargai keputusan Papa.
By not respecting my decision?
Terus, lo enggak menghargai keputusan gue?
Be happy you two.
Bahagia lo berdua.
- Your mother is a prostitute! - She's a slut!
Pelacur ibumu! Pelacur!
Slut!
Mbokmu itu pelacur!
Open your mouth!
Buka mulutmu! Mangap!
Where am I?
Gue ada di mana, ya?
You've had an accident
Mas habis kecelakaan.
and have been unconscious for four days.
Udah empat hari enggak sadarkan diri.
You have to rest now.
Sekarang, istirahat dulu saja, ya?
Four days?
Empat hari, ya?
No way.
Enggak mungkin.
I have a food test.
Aku harus uji makanan.
You can eat it first,
Makan dulu, ya, Pak.
after that drink this medicine.
Setelah itu minum obat.
I put the medicine in here.
Obatnya ada di sebelah sini.
I'm sorry, Sir.
Kenapa, Pak?
It's hospital food, of course it's not delicious.
Namanya juga makanan rumah sakit.
What are you doing here?
Ngapain lo ke sini?
I brought your favorite pasta.
Bawain pasta favorit kamu.
I also want to talk about your dream.
Sama mau ngobrolin mimpi kamu.
I know...
Aku tau
that Maharasa is not in your hands now,
kalo kamu udah enggak mengelola Maharasa lagi,
but I asked Papa to still invest in your restaurant.
tapi aku tetep nyuruh Papa berinvestasi.
He agrees, Ressa.
Papa setuju, Res.
He wants to give you more time.
Papa mau ngasih kamu waktu
We will have the food test...
tujuh hari setelah kamu dari rumah sakit,
seven days after you're discharged.
untuk uji makanan.
I believe that...
Aku yakin
you could invent an amazing dish...
kalo kamu bisa ngawinin
by combining the Italian and Indonesian food.
makanan Italia dengan Nusantara.
You could transform...
Kamu bisa ubah
a simple dish into something mind-blowing.
menu yang sederhana dengan sajian yang mencengangkan.
Good luck, Ressa.
Semoga berhasil, Res.
I can smell the food
Pas saya cium,
if I try to sniff it.
baunya ada semua, Dok.
But if I try to eat it...
Tapi kalo saya nyobain makan, nih...
whether it is salty or sweet...
Mau yang asin, mau yang manis,
I can't taste anything.
saya enggak bisa ngerasain, Dok.
What happened?
Kenapa bisa gitu?
My hypothesis is that...
Bisa jadi ini...
it could linked...
berkaitan dengan
to stress or trauma.
stres atau trauma.
Let me schedule a meeting
Nanti saya aturkan jadwal saja
with a psychiatrist.
dengan dokter Sp.KJ.
Or do you have someone in mind?
Atau Mas Ressa punya referensi?
I have.
Ada.
Dr. Sanusi.
Dokter Sanusi namanya.
Alright.
Baik.
I will call Dr. Sanusi.
Nanti saya akan hubungi Dokter Sanusi.
It's been five months since the last time we met.
Terakhir kita ketemu itu lima bulan yang lalu, ya, Res.
- And now, you're here because... - Doctor.
- Sekarang kontrol rujukan... - Dok...
What's wrong with my body?
Badan aku ini kenapa, Dok, ya?
Dr. Bambang said it could be...
Tadi Dokter Bambang bilang
linked to some trauma.
ini bisa ada hubungannya sama trauma.
Okay, I know that...
Ya, oke, aku tau
I can't smell local spices...
aku enggak bisa nyium bumbu-bumbu lokal.
because they bullied me
Karena pas kecil dirundung habis-habisan.
by forcing me to swallow a shrimp paste.
Dicekokin terasi.
But now, I can't even taste anything!
Tapi masa sekarang lidahku mati, Dok?
The good news is...
Kabar baiknya,
Dr. Bambang said that
Dokter Bambang itu bilang
there's nothing wrong with your tongue. All clear.
kalo hasil observasi lidah kamu tuh bagus, kok. Enggak ada masalah.
But the bad news is I cant taste anything.
Ya, tapi kabar buruknya, lidah aku mati rasa, Dok.
Look, Doctor.
Nih, Dok.
I will have a food tasting.
Aku akan ada uji makanan,
A very important event for me,
sesuatu yang sangat penting bagi aku,
for my career, for my dreams.
bagi karier aku, bagi impian aku.
Please give me
Aku minta tolong sama Dokter,
a medicine that could heal me
Dokter kasih aku obat yang bisa sembuhin
in an instant.
ini semua dengan cepat.
Alright, Doctor?
Oke, Dok?
Do not bring up that "make peace with your past," agenda.
Dokter jangan bawa-bawa, "Berdamai dengan masa lalu."
I didn't say anything.
Saya ini belom ngomong apa-apa, lho.
You always say that.
Abisnya dari dulu, selalu ngomongnya kayak begitu.
Okay.
Oke...
When will the food tasting be held?
Emang kapan uji makanannya?
Next week.
Minggu depan.
You have enough time to go to Magelang, then.
Cukup lah, buat ke Magelang? Ya, 'kan?
Eh, Ressa.
Eh, Res.
What's the name of your childhood friend?
Siapa tuh teman masa kecil kamu?
Tika, right?
Tika, 'kan?
Maybe you could heal your taste buds
Siapa tau kangennya kamu sama Tika
by meeting her.
bisa nyembuhin lidah kamu kayak dulu, lho.
There should be another way, Doctor.
Emang enggak ada cara lain apa Dok?
Ressa.
Res.
Listen. Let say you're a building,
Ibarat bangunan,
you're a beautiful skyscraper.
kamu ini adalah gedung indah yang menjulang tinggi.
But you don't have a sturdy foundation.
Tapi sayang, basemennya tuh enggak kokoh.
So, the building could collapse anytime.
Jadi, bisa bikin bangunannya tuh ambrol kapan saja.
Then, how can you make a good plan for the future?
Bagaimana kamu bisa merancang masa depan dengan baik?
Here.
Nih.
To relieve your stress.
Buat ngilangin stres.
Thank you, Doctor.
Makasih, Dok.
I will excuse myself.
Aku pergi dulu, ya.
Please consider my advice.
Inget omonganku tadi.
Thank you.
Makasih.
I can't believe it!
Tega lo, ya?
You're cheating on our anniversary!
Di hari jadi kita, lo bisa selingkuh!
She's mine now.
Dinda sekarang punya gue.
Papa asked Alex to handle the new concept of Maharasa.
Papa mau Alex mengurus konsep Maharasa yang baru.
The localized one.
Yang lebih lokal.
The one that is more Indonesian.
Yang lebih Nusantara.
Good morning Indonesia!
Selamat pagi, Indonesia.
You're back with me, Rahma Salsa.
Balik lagi bersama saya, Rahma Salsa.
Today, I'm going to invite you to...
Kali ini, saya mau mengajak kalian untuk menelusuri...
Maybe you could heal your taste buds by meeting her.
Siapa tau kangen kamu sama Tika bisa nyembuhin lidah kamu kayak dulu, lho.
...Sindoro hillside.
...kaki Gunung Sindoro.
Are you ready to start your journey with me?
Sudah siap menjelajah bareng saya?
And here is our Magelang special episode.
Inilah perjalanan rasa edisi Magelang!
Come here with me.
Ayo, sini. Sama Papa.
I'll teach you.
Saya ajarin.
Cut it like this.
Begini. Terus, potong gini. Ya?
Try it.
Coba.
Smart boy.
Nah, pinter.
Open your mouth!
Buka!
Go away!
Bubar! Minggat!
Rosso!
Roso.
Are you okay?
Kamu enggak apa-apa, 'kan?
Here, put it on your tongue.
Diemut aja.
It will help.
Nanti bakalan sembuh, kok.
Thank you.
- Makasih. - Ya.
Your monthly security fees.
Jadwal rutinan.
I don't have the money, Sir.
Belom ada duit, Pak.
I have to use it to pay the interest to my boss.
Lagian harganya dinaikin cukong-cukong, kok.
Do you want me to destroy this place?
Ini bisa, lho, ngobrak-ngabrik sayurmu!
Alright, I'll pay you.
Iya, Pak! Saya bayar!
- Spare me. - Hey, come here!
- Mas, jangan! - Ke sini kamu!
Son of a prostitute!
Anak pelacur!
- You, a prostitute's son! - Come here!
- Hei! - Anak pelacur!
Rosso, you're a prostitute's son.
Roso! Anak pelacur!
How dare you!
Berani-beraninya, ya!
You deserve it!
Syukurin!
Here.
Sut!
Open your mouth! Open it!
Mangap! Buka mulutmu!
Rosso Surosso!
Roso Suroso!
Finally you're back.
Akhirnya balik!
You're so handsome now!
Ganteng banget kamu!
You smell nice.
Wanginya!
You're Rosso Surosso, right?
Bener, 'kan, kamu Roso Suroso?
No, you're mistaken.
Maaf, salah orang.
How can I be?
Salah orang gimana?
I'm Tarjo. Do I look very different now?
Aku Tarjo. Kamu enggak kenal aku?
We're still the same, though.
Enggak rindu sama teman-teman?
Take off your sunglasses.
Makanya, kacamata dicopot dulu.
So you can see me clearly.
Biar aku ganteng juga.
Is your prostitute mother in Jakarta already gone?
Jadi pelacur di Jakarta enggak laku, ya?
Is that why you're back?
Makanya kamu pulang?
Alumni of prostitutes are back!
Alumni pelacuran pulang.
I could even smell sperm on the sunglasses.
Kacamatanya bau sperma!
Let's go.
Enggak jadi!
Everyone, the prostitute's son is back!
Eh, anaknya pelacur udah balik, lho, Mbak!
What a nice thing to see.
Keren!
What's wrong with you?
- Kenapa kamu? - Ya Allah!
Fuck you!
Anjing!
Bastard!
Bangsat!
Mind your own business, Tika!
Enggak usah ikut campur, Tik!
You never stop!
Enggak kapok, ya?
Damn you, Tika.
Anjing, Tik...
Just give up!
Nyerah, enggak?
Alright, Tika!
Iya, Tik.
Tika, stop!
Ampun. Udah, Tik.
Let's go!
Ayo balik!
Come on.
Pergi!
Damn you.
Dasar kau!
Tika.
Tik.
Just go back.
Balik sana.
I don't know you anymore.
Kita udah enggak kenal lagi.
Have you called Tika?
Udah ditelepon?
I have.
- Si Tika? - Udah.
Why is she so slow?
Mana?
Gareng! Help me!
Mang Gareng! Yuk! Bantuin!
Alright.
Iya...
She brings so many things.
Repot banget.
Tika, why are the vegetables not fresh?
Ini kurang seger, Tik!
The tomatos are crushed!
Tomat ancur.
Because of Tarjo.
Gara-gara si Tarjo.
Tarjo the thug?
Tarjo tengkulak?
So that's why you're late.
Pantes kesiangan.
Ah, that's right.
Walah, pantes!
It's the time they ask for money from the shop.
Tanggal tua, jatahnya narik duit ke pedagang.
What's wrong with your hands?
Tanganmu kenapa ini?
Did you fight with them?
Berantem, ya?
A little bit.
Sebentar.
A lady shouldn't be fighting.
Anak perempuan kok sukanya berantem?
The coriander please.
Ketumbar...
A lady should cook.
Harusnya masak.
Work hard, so you can have a lot of money.
Rajin cari duit yang banyak.
I'm tired of cooking.
Bosen masak terus.
You always have an answer.
Jawab, lho.
- Here, thank you. - You're welcome.
- Terima kasih, ya. - Sama-sama, Om.
Why are they not open yet?
Oh, jam segini kok belum buka, ya?
They're not open yet.
- Hei, apa... - Aduh, Pak.
Where are you from?
Mas dari mana?
Jogja, Sir.
- Kami dari Jogja, Pak. - Wah.
Jogja? That's far!
Jogja? Jauh banget.
Yes, we set off early,
Iya, kita berangkat lebih pagi
so we can grab a seat here.
supaya dapet tempat duduk.
People said the Mangut they serve is very delicious.
Katanya, mangutnya enak banget, lho!
That's right.
Iya. Betul, Pak.
If you're cooking from the heart, the food will be delicious.
Masak itu kalau senang, pasti enak.
Am I right, Gareng?
Benar, enggak, Reng?
Sis.
Mbluk.
Pass me the lemongrass and the lime leaves.
Serai sama daun jeruk.
Welcome!
Selamat datang!
No need to worry!
Tenang.
We made a big portion for everyone.
Hari ini, kami masak banyak. Semua pasti kebagian!
Please come in.
Silakan masuk!
Let's go in.
Masuk.
Come in, come in.
Mari!
What about the drinks?
Minumnya apa?
- Ice tea. - Then it will be Rp27.000.
Es teh?
Done, right?
Udah?
Rp27.000, right?
Dua tujuh, 'kan, ya?
The change amount is...
Kembaliannya berarti...
Wait a moment. Here's the change.
Kembaliannya, ini.
- I'm going back. - Take care.
- Pulang dulu, ya. - Hati-hati, ya.
Okay.
- Ya. - Mari, Mbak.
Send my regards to Grandma.
Hei, salam buat Simbah!
- Tika. - What do you want?
- Tik. - Apa lagi, sih?
I need to talk to you.
Aku harus ngobrol sama kamu.
I don't want to. Give it back!
Enggak mau aku. Balikin.
- Just talk for a moment. - Give my key back!
- Bentar doang, Tik! - Balikin kunciku!
Give it back!
Sini!
I'll give it back to you once we're talking.
Enggak akan aku balikin sebelum kita ngobrol.
Oh, my...
Reng...
Tika!
Tik!
Let's talk for a while, okay?
Ngobrol bentar. Bentar aja.
Okay?
Oke?
Who is it?
Siapa itu, Mbak?
I don't know either.
Aku juga enggak tau.
Here's your drink.
Ini minumnya, Mas.
Thank you.
Terima kasih, ya.
You're welcome.
Sama-sama.
right?
Enggak apa-apa, 'kan?
It's okay.
Enggak apa-apa.
Just go home.
Ya udah, pulang aja, Mbak.
I'll close the restaurant later.
Nanti biar aku yang tutup warung.
Everything is okay, right?
Aman, 'kan, Mas?
- Yes. - Of course! It should be okay!
- Aman. - Harus aman.
You force them to be okay!
Maksa, lho, kamu.
Alright, Tika.
Udah, ya, Tik.
We'll go.
Pamit aku.
Take care.
Hati-hati.
Tika.
Tik.
I came here to ask you for a favor.
Aku sebenarnya ke sini mau minta tolong.
Years of no words
Ilang bertaun-taun,
and you come back here for a favor?
dateng-dateng minta tolong.
I know I was wrong.
Iya, aku tau aku salah.
I'm sorry.
Aku minta maaf.
I know you're angry because I didn't reply to all your letters, right?
Kamu bete, 'kan, karena aku enggak bales surat-surat kamu?
You think I don't wanna talk to you
Kamu pikir aku enggak mau kenal sama kamu lagi
just because of that?
cuma gara-gara itu?
Then,
Ya, terus?
why are you angry?
Gara-gara apa?
Anyway...
Omong-omong...
for everyone at home,
Mungkin buat yang di rumah, nih,
you may already know that Chef Ressa
sempet tau juga kalo Chef Ressa ini
- was born in Jakarta. - Right.
- emang lahir sebenernya di Jakarta. - Ya.
But raised in Italy with your father,
Tumbuh barengan sama bokap lo di Italia.
- then you came back to Jakarta. - That's right.
- Nah, terus lo balik lagi ke Jakarta. - Betul.
- Until today? - Yes, since then I'm staying here.
- Sampe sekarang? Sampe hari ini? - Sampe hari ini.
Okay.
Oke.
I heard when you and your assistant are talking,
Ya, lo tadi lagi sama asisten lu.
and I think I hear you're talking in...
Gue denger gitu, kayak lo ngomong...
I know this place is only a small village,
Tempat ini memang desa.
that is full of poor farmers who's fate has always
Isinya petani miskin yang nasibnya
been played by those rich people from Jakarta.
selalu dimainin sama cukong pangan dari Jakarta-mu itu.
- Tika. - You're lying to the public.
- Tik... - Yang kamu lakuin itu kebohongan publik.
And the worst thing is...
Dan yang paling parah...
you're lying to Grandma,
kamu bohongin Simbah
who took care of you all this time.
yang udah ngerawat kamu.
What are you expecting?
Ya, terus menurutmu aku harus bagaimana?
Tell the world that I was adopted?
Ngomong ke semua orang kalo aku tuh anak pungut?
Is that it?
Gitu?
Tell them that I as a Chef,
Bilang ke semua orang kalo aku sebagai chef
I can't smell local spices,
mual-mual, muntah-muntah
or else I'll throw up?
kalo nyium bumbu-bumbu lokal? Gitu?
I don't know!
Ya, aku enggak tau.
But I know for sure, you already forgot this place.
Tapi yang pasti kamu udah lupain tempat ini dari hidupmu, 'kan?
Rosso.
Roso.
For your information,
Asal kamu tau,
everyone here is proud of you
warga di sini banyak yang bangga sama kamu
because you are a very successful Chef in Jakarta.
karena kamu berhasil di Jakarta.
Many of them even think that
Bahkan banyak yang ngira
you became an incredible Chef
kamu jadi chef beken
because of this restaurant.
gara-gara warung ini.
You don't know that, do you?
Enggak tau, 'kan, kamu?
But it is what it is.
Udahlah.
It's already in the past.
Udah lewat.
And now me,
Sekarang aku,
Grandma,
Simbah,
and you,
kamu...
should continue our lives separately like before.
udah punya hidup masing-masing.
So, just enjoy this town like many tourists
Jadi, sekarang silakan kamu nikmati desa ini
who come here for healing.
layaknya orang kota lagi memulihkan diri.
I'm going home.
Aku pulang.
Tika.
Tik.
Wait.
Tunggu.
I wanna see Grandma.
Aku mau ketemu Simbah.
Bet you will throw up.
Enggak takut muntah?
Since Grandma's house is full of local spices.
Rumah Simbah 'kan isinya bumbu lokal.
Oh my God!
Ya Allah.
Your Grandma is in her bedroom with Grandpa Darmo.
Simbahmu di kamar sama Mbah Darmo.
- See your Grandma first. - Okay.
Udah, kamu masuk dulu sana.
Grandma.
Mbah.
Asked her to drink this, Tika.
Ini, lho, Tik.
I already made...
Sudah aku kasih minum
tumeric with garlic...
tumbukan kunyit dan bawang putih,
and a little bit of palm sugar.
dicampur gula jawa sedikit.
Thank you.
Terima kasih, ya.
Please,
Silakan, Mas.
have a seat.
Silakan duduk dulu.
Yes, thank you.
Iya, Pak.
Let's go.
Ayo. Hus.
Come on.
Masuk.
Sir.
Eh, Pak.
That man...
Mas itu
He's like a celebrity
kok kayak artis, ya?
He's not an artist, Yu!
Bukan artis, Mbak.
He's a Chef.
Dia itu chef.
Ressa, I made...
Ini, lho.
Tika's favorite food.
Simbah masakin makanan kesukaan Tika.
Have a try.
Dicoba, ya?
Is it tasty?
Enak, 'kan, Nak?
Very tasty, Grandma!
Enak banget, Mbah!
Eat more, okay.
Tambah, ya? Tambah?
Rosso.
So.
Rosso Suroso.
Roso Suroso.
What a good name.
Nama kamu bagus.
Rosso means strength.
Roso itu artinya "kuat".
It could also mean taste.
Juga bisa berarti "rasa".
And Suroso, it means "enlighten".
Jadi, Suroso itu "wibawa".
Then, if we combine Rosso Suroso...
Kalau disatukan "Roso Suroso",
it means "the strength that is enlightening".
"kekuatan yang berwibawa".
Or taste that is enlightening?
Apa rasa yang berwibawa?
What a smart boy!
Aduh, pinter kamu, Nak!
Continue eating, Rosso.
Ayo, lanjutin lagi makannya. Pelan-pelan makannya.
- Tika, eat more. - Yes, Grandma.
- Ayo, Tika. Ditambah lagi. - Sudah, Mbah.
Really?
- Tukang masak. - Walah.
How can a Chef be so handsome?
Tukang masak kok ganteng banget, ya?
Yes, he's handsome.
Iya. Ganteng, ya?
He must've taken care of himself well.
Pasti orang kota, ya? Iya, 'kan?
You're right.
Iya.
Young man, I'm sorry.
Mas. Maaf.
Are you Chef Ressa...
Ini teh Chef Ressa, ya?
that we've seen on TV?
Yang sering nongol di TV itu, ya?
That's right, Sir.
- Iya, Pak. - Walah.
The one who likes to throw away...
Yang suka buang makanan di tempat sampah
the untasteful food to the trash bin?
kalo makanannya enggak enak itu, 'kan?
Yes.
Iya.
Oh my.
Aduh!
Can I ask for a photo?
Saya boleh foto, enggak, Mas?
Sure.
Boleh.
Yu! Take a photo of me and him.
Mbak, ke sini.
- Photo? - Yeah.
- Foto? - Ayo.
Grandpa Darmo,
Mbah Darmo kok
why are you here?
bisa kebetulan ada di sini?
I had a bad feeling since the afternoon.
Hatiku merasa enggak enak dari tadi sore.
I was thinking about your Grandma.
Aku ingat mbahmu.
That's why I'm here.
Makanya, aku buru-buru kemari.
When I arrived
Eh, sampe teras depan,
I heard a loud sound.
- kedengeran gedubrakan. - Terus?
- What happened? - I thought there was a thief.
Aku pikir maling.
But it turns out your Grandma...
Ternyata mbahmu jatuh di pinggir sumur.
Rosso.
So...
Grandma?
Mbah?
Smile! One, two, three.
- Senyum. - Satu, dua, tiga...
Rosso.
So...
Who's outside?
Ada siapa di depan?
Why is it so loud outside?
Pak RT rame sama siapa, ya?
- Done. - Let me look at the photos.
- Udah. Nah... - Kayak apa? Lihat, dong. Lihat.
- Let me see. - One more thing,
Oh, iya, Mas. Maaf.
is it true that...
Apa benar Mas Ressa itu
you're from this town?
asli sini, ya?
He was raised here.
Dia kecilnya di sini, Pak RT.
Grandma took care of him.
Diurusin Mbah juga.
Rosso. Grandma is looking for you.
Roso, Simbah nyariin.
- I'm going in first, Sir. - Sure, sure.
- Duluan, ya, Pak. - Iya, silakan.
- Ma'am. - Go ahead.
- Bu. - Iya.
Rosso...
Roso...
I wanna see you, Rosso.
Simbah ingin ketemu kamu, So.
Grandpa.
Mbah.
Rosso.
So...
Grandma.
Mbah?
I'm here. This is Rosso.
Ini Roso, Mbah.
Thank God!
Gusti Allah.
You're back now.
Kamu pulang, Nak.
I'm home, Grandma.
Roso udah pulang, Mbah.
What's wrong?
Kenapa kamu?
Are you gonna throw up?
Mau muntah?
What's wrong, Rosso?
Ada masalah apa, Nak?
Grandma.
Mbah.
You shouldn't be nice to him.
Enggak usah terlalu baik sama dia.
He already forgot us.
Dia aja udah lupa sama Simbah.
Is that true?
Masa, sih?
Ask him yourself.
Tanya aja sendiri.
He doesn't even want to mention this village.
Sebut nama desa ini aja udah enggak mau.
Am I right?
Ya, 'kan?
We can't measure whether someone...
Seseorang mengingat atau tidak,
remembers us or not by...
bukan diukur
how often they call our names.
dari berapa seringnya dia menyebut nama.
Our memory is here...
"Ingat" itu di sini,
and here.
sama di sini.
If he misses us, then he remember us.
Kalo dia bisa merasakan, pasti masih ingat.
Don't force yourself...
Kalo enggak bisa makan makanan desa,
if you can't eat this village's food.
enggak usah maksa.
Mustika.
Mustika.
Grandma, I can't taste anything.
Lidah aku mati rasa, Mbah.
How come?
Kok bisa?
A problematic man.
Problematik.
Nausea if you smell local spices.
Mual nyium bumbu lokal.
Loses his taste buds.
Lidah mati rasa.
I'm not lying, Tika.
Aku enggak bohong, Tik.
Mustika!
Mustika!
Eat this.
Makan.
Show me if you lost your taste buds.
Buktiin kalo lidahmu mati rasa.
Oh My God!
Gusti Allah!
What happened to you?
Kamu ini kenapa?
I was in car accident, Grandma.
Aku abis kecelakaan, Mbah.
I was unconscious for days,
Aku ilang kesadaran.
but when I woke up,
Pas aku bangun, tiba-tiba
I had already lost my taste buds.
lidahku mati rasa.
I can smell everything.
Aku masih bisa nyium,
But...
tapi
my tongue can't taste anything.
lidahku mati rasa total.
The doctor said...
Kata dokter,
- it might be caused by... - Stress?
- mungkin karena... - Stres?
Or unfinished trauma?
Trauma belom selesai?
Come with me.
Ikut Simbah.
Where are we going, Grandma?
Kita mau ke mana, Mbah?
Just follow me.
Udah, ikut aja.
As long as the soul is here,
Selama roh masih ada,
there's no way the taste buds die.
rasa tidak akan mati.
They're only asleep.
Dia cuma tertidur.
Your chaotic mind caused all of that.
Disebabkan kekacauan pikiranmu sendiri.
Bring me the water, Tika.
Tika, airnya!
- Here, Grandma. - Here.
- Sini. - Ini, Mbah.
Enough.
Udah.
Drink it.
Minum.
What is that?
Itu apa, Mbah, isinya?
What a fussy man! Just drink it!
Duh! Rewel amat. Orang tinggal minum, kok!
You don't wanna be cured?
Mau sembuh, enggak?
Drink it.
Ayo minum.
I can't stand the smell.
Aku enggak kuat, Mbah, ama baunya.
Bear with it.
Harus ditahan.
Drink it, Rosso.
Ayo minum!
Is it done? Finish it!
Udah? Habisin.
If you're feeling dizzy,
Kalo kamu merasa pusing,
that means the medicine is working.
itu obatnya sedang bekerja.
Have you cleaned up his room?
Kamarnya udah dibereskan, belom?
Not yet.
Belom.
He can't stand by himself if he's giddy.
Ini kasihan, lho, kalo udah begini.
What time is it?
Jam berapa sekarang?
It's 7 o'clock.
Itu. Jam tujuh.
I have to go to the restaurant.
Tika enggak bisa. Harus ke warung.
Wait up, Tika.
Lho, sebentar.
He's already unsteady.
Ini udah pusing-pusing begitu.
- Help him! - Grandma.
- Ayo, pegangin! - Mbah.
I'm not strong enough to help him!
Simbah enggak kuat!
Hurry up!
Cepet!
Slowly.
Tolong, ya.
Put me down here.
- Sini, Tik. Sini. - Ha?
Grandma.
Mbah.
Let's eat, Rosso.
Roso, makan.
Come here.
Sini, Nak.
Grandma.
Ya, Mbah.
Here.
Ini.
Let's eat.
Ini, makan.
Thank you, Grandma.
Makasih, Mbah.
For you, Grandma.
Silakan, Mbah.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Eat up, Rosso, try it.
- Ayo, dimakan. Dicoba. - Ya.
I'm famished!
Laper.
Is it nice?
Enak, 'kan?
It's delicious!
Enak.
You already woke up?
Udah bangun?
You slept like a dead man.
Tidur kayak orang mati.
What do you mean? I only slept for an hour.
Apaan, sih? Orang cuma sejam.
An hour?
Sejam?
You're dreaming.
Halu.
I slept for an hour!
Sejam.
Grandma.
- Mbah. - Hmm?
Did I sleep for 25 hours?
Aku tidur 25 jam?
That means your body needs a total rest.
Ya, berarti tubuhmu perlu istirahat total.
Are you that stressed in Jakarta?
Kamu stres, ya, di Jakarta?
He's stressed because he lies every day.
Orang tiap hari kerjanya bohongin diri sendiri.
Tika!
- Gimana enggak... - Tika!
I'm right, aren't I?
Bener, 'kan?
She's not wrong, Grandma.
Tika enggak salah, Mbah.
Ever since I moved to Jakarta,
Sejak aku pindah ke Jakarta...
I started to forget my true self.
...pelan-pelan aku lupa siapa diri aku sebenarnya.
My mother, she changed my name...
Ibu aku ganti nama aku
so I could start a new life,
supaya aku bisa mulai hidup baru.
and also...
Supaya aku juga
forget my childhood trauma.
melupakan trauma kecil aku.
But I don't know why,
Tapi setelah itu tuh,
I always strive for the best.
aku enggak tau kenapa, aku selalu ada perasaan ingin jadi yang terbaik di rumah.
I keep chasing things...
Mengejar ini, mengejar itu.
even though no one asked me to.
Kayak ada yang maksa, padahal enggak ada yang nyuruh, Mbah.
For me...
Dan...
that's tiring.
itu lumayan melelahkan.
Even just hearing it makes me exhausted.
Aku yang dengar aja capek.
Tika!
Tika.
Is that spicy?
Kepedesan?
Yes.
He-em.
Didn't you say you lost your taste buds?
Katanya lidahmu mati rasa?
That's a quick reaction.
Bener sakit, enggak, sih?
Are you really sick?
Cepet banget sembuhnya.
Grandma.
Mbah.
I'm cured.
Lidahku sembuh.
You don't believe in...
Tika, kamu...
my traditional medicine potion, do you?
enggak percaya kehebatan ramuan rempahnya Simbah?
That's not true, but usually it's not that fast.
Enggak gitu, Mbah. Biasanya 'kan enggak secepet ini.
Each body reacts to the potion differently.
Masing-masing tubuh reaksinya berbeda-beda.
But, the effect isn't permanent.
Efek obat itu tidak permanen.
You shouldn't feel relief yet.
Jangan terlena.
You might lose your taste buds again
Lidahmu, kalo mati rasa kembali, karena mungkin
if your mind is still a mess.
pikiranmu masih ruwet.
The potion only helps you to tone down the problem.
Obat itu hanya membantu tubuh memerangi penyakit.
You're the only one who knows...
Ya, sesungguhnya, obat yang sebenarnya
how to cure it.
adalah diri sendiri.
But Grandma,
Tapi, Mbah...
how long will the effect last?
kira-kira, obat ini bertahan berapa lama?
I have to go back to Jakarta,
Aku harus pulang ke Jakarta.
because I have to do a food tasting.
Ada uji makanan yang harus aku lakuin.
It will only last for three days.
Efek obat itu paling lama bertahan tiga hari.
But I won't stop you if you want to go back to Jakarta.
Tapi kalo mau pulang, ya, silakan aja.
But I can't do anything,
Kalo lidahmu mati rasa lagi,
if you lose your taste buds again.
Simbah enggak bisa nolong kamu.
Your Grandma's potion is a stress reliever.
Ramuan mbahmu itu termasuk obat pereda stres.
It's the same thing as the antidepressant
Semacam antidepresan
that I gave you before,
yang sudah saya resepkan,
but you said...
tapi kamu bilang
it doesn't work.
enggak berefek banyak buat kondisimu.
There's no clinical explanation...
Ya, meskipun enggak teruji secara klinis,
but it's a complementary medicine,
ada yang namanya "complementary medicine",
or it is called alternative treatment.
alias pengobatan alternatif.
I advise you to continue your stay there.
Ada baiknya kamu lanjutkan rehat kamu di sana, Res.
Enjoy the fresh air and the peaceful town.
Nikmati cuaca sejuk, suasana tenang.
It might be...
Yah, siapa tau...
that you not only cure your taste buds,
bukan hanya lidah kamu yang membaik,
but also your childhood trauma.
tapi trauma masa kecil kamu juga.
The Mangut, a fish dish with coconut sauce
Lho? Mangutnya kok
is completely sold out!
habis ini, Mbak?
Please, wait a moment.
- Iya, sabar. Tenang. - Tenang.
Alright, alright. Please wait a moment.
- Habis. - Iya, oke. Sebentar...
Please serve more Mangut.
Tik!
Tika, hurry up!
Tik! Ngebut, Tik!
I only have two hands!
Udah ngebut, ini tanganku cuma dua! Ah!
Oh My God, be careful.
Oh! Hati-hati! Eh!
The plaster is there!
Tuh! Ambil!
Come on, where is it?
Bikin lagi, dong.
- I'm very hungry! - Where is it?
Tenang! Sebentar!
Gareng.
Reng!
Where is it?
- Mas! Kapan, Mas? - Gareng!
Please wait a moment.
Sabar. Iya...
Hurry up, Tika!
- Tik! Ngebut, Tik! - Cepetan!
Wait!
Sabar!
Let me help you.
Biarin. Sini, aku bantu.
No one asked you to come here.
Siapa yang suruh kamu masuk sini, sih?
Just let me help you.
Udah, biar aku bantuin. Ya?
Please wait for 30 minutes.
Lagi dimasak...
Where is it? We're hungry!
Laper banget ini.
- We waited a long time. - I am hungry!
Aku dari tadi!
Everyone calm down.
Tenang... Semuanya, tenang. Tenang.
I'm going to cook Mangut with my own recipe.
Di sini, aku akan bantu memasak mangut dengan resep aku.
Of course,
Tentu
without changing...
dengan tidak mengubah cita rasa
the uniqueness of this place.
warung makan ini.
Don't try to seek attention.
- Ya? - Enggak usah cari perhatian, deh.
This is not an Italian restaurant!
Ini bukan warung Italia.
Alright, let's have a bet, then.
Kalo begitu, kita taruhan aja.
If the taste is...
Kalo sampai
not up to this restaurant's standard,
rasanya tidak sesuai,
or unsatisfying.
tidak enak,
I will pay you Rp100,000.
aku bayar kamu 100.000.
But if it's on par...
Tapi kalo misalnya rasanya sesuai
or above your standard,
atau mungkin lebih enak,
you're the one who will pay me Rp100,000.
kamu yang bayar aku 100.000.
How about that?
Gimana?
- What's going on? - Do we agree?
- Ini malah pada ngapain? - Setuju, Semuanya?
Agree!
Setuju!
Calm down, Sis.
Tenang, yuk...
I will help you.
Aku bantu... Oke?
I put my bet on you!
Aku bertaruh buat kamu, Mas!
Come on.
- Mantap! - Ayo.
Okay.
Ya udah! Ayo...
Let me cut this one.
Biar aku lanjut potong,
You can work on this one.
kamu lanjut di sini.
Please hurry up!
Ya?
It's still in progress.
Ya, itu lagi dibuat! Oke?
Please wait.
Santai, ya?
Isn't that Chef Ressa?
Itu bukannya Chef Ressa?
I'll take a video of him!
- Mana, sih? Foto! - Hei!
Do not film this!
Jangan rekam! Suruh jangan rekam-rekam!
- Go away. - Do not film this.
Jangan rekam-rekam!
Please, wait in line so that everyone could get some.
Antre, ya! Satu-satu, biar kebagian semua.
The potion only helps you to tone down the problem.
Obat itu hanya membantu tubuh memerangi penyakit.
You're the only one who knows...
Obat yang sebenarnya
how to cure it.
adalah diri sendiri.
Rosso.
Roso.
Are you okay, Rosso?
Kamu enggak apa-apa, 'kan?
How's the Mangut?
Mas, gimana mangutnya?
Very delicious!
- Jos, Mas! - Wah.
The taste of this Mangut is different!
Mangut yang ini beda, Mas.
It's tastier than the usual.
Enak banget rasanya.
Did you change the cook?
Ini yang masak beda, ya?
Of course, she is.
Masih sama, Mas!
- Still the same person? - Yeah, we're still on the same team.
- Masih sama? - Masih satu tim.
Everything is so delicious.
Semuanya sama. Enak banget.
Okay, if you want to eat it again,
Nanti kalo mau tambah,
you can go directly to the buffet.
langsung aja, ya, Mas.
Of course I will!
Oh, iya. Oh, ini pasti tambah, sih.
Chef! Move, move!
Chef! Bang, minggir, Bang!
Chef Ressa, Chef Ressa!
- Chef! - Mana, sih?
Move, move!
Minggir, Bang!
Do not film it.
Jangan rekam.
- Chef Ressa, Chef Ressa! - Chef!
- Chef Ressa! Chef! - Chef Ressa!
It's so cool that...
- Keren, ya? - Chef.
Chef Ressa cooks for us!
- Dimasakin Chef Ressa! - Wah. Chef Ressa.
My God! Do not disturb me!
Apa, sih? Gangguin aja lo.
- Chef Ressa! - Stop it.
- Chef Ressa. - Stop, hei
Chef Ressa.
Ganteng banget.
I admit, I lose.
Aku ngaku kalah.
Gareng.
Mas Gareng.
Yes?
Iya, Mas.
Thank you for your support.
Makasih dukungannya.
I can use it for a cooperative deposit!
Lumayan, buat setor koperasi.
If I want to be a cook here,
Kalo mau daftar jadi chef di sini...
where should I send my resume?
kirim CV-nya ke mana?
Or maybe I could just help around, right?
Langsung aja kali, ya? Enggak usah daftar-daftaran.
Have you seen this?
Udah lihat ini, belom?
Chef Ressa, Chef Ressa!
- Chef... - Sama...
Thank you...
Makasih, ya,
for helping in the restaurant.
udah bantu warung.
And thank you, for letting me cook in your restaurant.
Makasih juga udah ngizinin aku masak di warung kamu.
Because of you, we already surpassed our target for this month.
Gara-gara kamu, pendapatan bulan ini memenuhi target.
I'm sorry.
Aku minta maaf.
I didn't treat you well before.
Sikapku sebelumnya enggak nyenengin banget.
It's okay.
Enggak apa-apa.
I deserve it.
Aku emang pantes digituin.
I was angry because I was brokenhearted.
Aku marah karena hatiku patah.
You...
Kamu...
who made my heart broken.
bikin aku patah hati.
I was jealous
Aku sempet cemburu waktu
when your Aunt came to pick you up.
tantemu dateng jemput kamu.
You had a new mom,
Akhirnya, kamu punya ibu lagi.
not like me.
Enggak kayak aku.
Tika.
Nak.
Who sent that letter?
Surat dari siapa?
It's a letter from Rosso, Grandma.
Dari Roso, Mbah.
Rosso?
Roso?
Yes.
Iya, Mbah.
I was so happy when you sent me that letter.
Aku seneng banget waktu kamu kirim surat.
I even...
Saking senengnya, aku
replied right away and told you my stories.
langsung bales, terus cerita panjang.
Excuse me, Ma'am.
Permisi, Bu.
- Sir. - Excuse me!
- Pak! - Dek! Ayo!
But your letter has never come again.
Habis itu, suratmu enggak pernah dateng lagi.
Tika!
Nak!
Even when I sent you several letters.
Padahal, aku udah tulis surat-berkali-kali.
When I already forgot about you,
Saat aku udah lupain kamu,
suddenly you're everywhere.
tiba-tiba kamu muncul.
Who is that?
Siapa itu?
It's Rosso, Grandma.
Roso, Mbah.
But...
Tapi
he changed his name to Ressa Eugino.
namanya ganti jadi Ressa Eugino.
I saw you.
Aku lihat kamu,
I watched all of your shows.
aku lihat acaramu.
There's something weird in my chest...
Setiap lihat kamu,
everytime I see you.
ada perasaan aneh di dadaku.
Grandma told me that...
Katanya Simbah...
what I feel is love.
itu cinta.
I even collected all of your articles...
Saking cintanya sama kamu,
just because I loved you dearly.
aku ngumpulin artikel-artikel tentang kamu.
Chef, me and Nat are hearing some rumours.
Chef, ini gue denger, nih, ya, sama si Nat kemaren.
Many people say that...
Katanya lo tuh enggak suka
you dislike local food and spices.
makanan lokal dan bumbu Indonesia.
Is that true?
Bener, enggak, sih?
As a chef,
Lo ini 'kan chef.
you're quite discriminating, aren't you?
Masa lo beda-bedain makanan, sih?
- Yeah, how come you do that - No, it's not like that.
- Iya. Gimana, deh? - Enggak, bukan begitu.
My speciality is Italian food,
Spesialisasi gue emang di Italian food. Masakan Italia.
which comes from my heritage.
Sesuai dengan warisan budaya gue.
Anyway, for everyone at home,
Omong-omong, mungkin buat yang di rumah, nih, sempet
you may already know that...
tau juga kalo
Chef Ressa was born in Jakarta.
Chef Ressa ini emang lahir sebenernya di Jakarta.
Right.
- Ya, 'kan? - Ya.
But you were raised in Italy with your father,
Tumbuh barengan sama bokap lo di Italia.
- then you came back to Jakarta. - That's right.
- Terus, lo balik lagi ke Jakarta. - Betul.
- Until today? - Yes, since then I've been staying here.
- Sampe sekarang? Hari ini? - Sampe hari ini.
Okay.
Oke.
I think I heard when...
Itu tadi, ya. Gue sempet sama...
Why did Rosso say that?
Roso kok ngomongnya begitu?
I know Rosso very well,
Itu bukan Roso, Mbah.
and I'm sure he's not the Rosso we know.
Tika tahu betul.
I felt the jealousy that I felt before,
Rasa cemburu yang dulu datang lagi,
and it started to become hatred.
pelan-pelan berubah jadi benci.
Since then, I never wanted to know you again.
Saat itu, aku enggak kenal sama kamu lagi.
I erased you from my life.
Roso udah bener-bener hilang.
I'm sorry, Tika.
Maafin aku, ya, Tik.
What happened?
Ini kenapa?
What happened with Maharasa?
Kenapa Maharasa sepi?
The food is unsatisfactory...
Harga terlalu mahal, dan...
yet it's overpriced, Sir.
tidak sebanding dengan rasanya, Bapak.
But we use Mustika Rasa recipes!
Tetapi Maharasa 'kan sudah pakai resep Mustikarasa!
It is supposed to be more than just satisfactory.
'Kan pasti makanannya baik dan enak!
This is not about Mustika Rasa, Sir.
Ini bukan tentang Mustikarasa.
Then what's wrong?
Apa jadinya?
The food doesn't rely on the recipe, Sir.
Karena rasa tidak bergantung dari resepnya, Bapak.
And?
Jadi?
It relies on the Chef himself.
Dari tangan seorang chef.
What's wrong with our Chef?
Kenapa dengan chef kita?
I think you should...
Saya pikir
Dinda!
Dinda.
Papa!
Pa.
Go home,
Kamu...
Now!
pulang.
Katherine.
Catherine.
Drive her home.
Tolong antar Dinda pulang.
Mr. Broto.
Pak Broto.
This is Mangut developed from Chef Alex's recipe.
Ini mangut resep Chef Alex.
Sir, I'm the executive chef,
Pak, itu seharusnya
I should be the one who cooks it.
yang masak saya, Pak. Saya executive chef-nya.
If you're the Executive Chef,
Kalo kamu chef,
you're supposed to be in the kitchen.
tempatmu di dapur,
Not in my office.
bukan di ruangan saya ini.
Now, I understand...
Pantes
why Maharasa is struggling.
Maharasa sepi.
- Out! - But, Sir, I think...
- Keluar. - Enggak. Seharusnya...
- But, Sir! But, Sir!
- Pak!
Out!
Keluar!
Sorry to interrupt, Sir.
Maaf, Pak.
Please, take a look at this.
Coba lihat ini.
Grandma Wongso's Restaurant is known as
Sudah lama Warung Mbah Wongso dikenal
the hotest place in Magelang.
paling laris di Magelang.
You guys must be familiar...
Nah, temen-temen pasti udah enggak asing
with this person, right?
dengan sosok yang satu ini.
Hello, good afternoon, Chef.
Halo, Chef. Selamat siang.
Hello.
- Halo. - Ya.
We're very curious, Chef. Why exactly...
Nah, ini yang bikin kita penasaran, ya.
- Ressa? - are you here?
- Kenapa Chef Ressa bisa ada di sini? - Ressa?
To tell you the truth,
Sebetulnya,
I've been lying for a long time.
- selama ini saya telah berbohong. - Oke.
I've told everyone that I was born in Jakarta,
- Dari dulu, saya bilang lahir di Jakarta. - Ya.
but it's not true.
Tapi itu tidak benar.
I was born in this village,
Sebetulnya, saya lahir di desa ini.
and I was raised by Grandma Wongso...
Dan sampe saya umur delapan tahun,
until I was eight years old.
saya dibesarkan oleh Mbah Wongso,
Then I moved to Jakarta when I was adopted.
sampe akhirnya saya diangkat anak ke Jakarta.
But now, I'm back...
Namun, saya sekarang merasa saya harus...
and would like to dedicate myself here.
membaktikan diri kembali ke sini.
So, I can...
Sekalian
help Tika...
bantuin Tika
and Grandma Wongso.
dan Mbah Wongso.
Okay. Alright, Tika, could you please tell us...
Oh, oke. Nah, Mbak Tika. Boleh, dong, dibocorin.
where did you get the recipes for the menu?
Resep menu-menu masakan di sini tuh dari mana?
Actually...
Kalo untuk resep itu,
All the recipes are Grandma Wongso's,
sebenernya, ya, dari Mbah Wongso sendiri.
since she collected many recipes...
Karena 'kan beliau juga punya banyak kumpulan
from Indonesia.
resep Nusantara.
Which makes us drool, right?
Pastinya akan menggoyang lidah kita semuanya.
Okay, thank you.
Oke, terima kasih banyak...
Grandma.
Silahkan, Mbah.
Try this one.
Dicicipi.
Okay.
Ya.
Is it nice?
Enak?
How is it?
Enak, Mbah?
Of course it is.
Enak.
But my tongue can't eat this type of noodle.
Tapi lidah Mbah enggak cocok mi seperti ini.
I would love to...
Rasanya mau tambah
add spices that were made by your Grandpa.
bumbu racikan eyangmu.
I could make you a new one,
Kalo gitu, mau...
if you want.
aku buatin yang baru?
Do you want it too?
Kamu mau juga, enggak?
There's no need.
Enggak usah. Ini aja.
I'm happy to see you both get along.
Simbah seneng melihat kalian akrab kembali seperti dulu.
You know...
Habisnya...
A week ago, your Grandpa...
Seminggu yang lalu, Simbah mimpi
came to my dream.
eyang kakungmu.
- Grandpa Darsono? - Yes.
- Eyang Darsono? - Iya.
Your Grandpa asked...
Terus Eyang bilang
why did I...
ama Simbah,
I forget and leave Rosso behind.
kenapa Simbah melupakan Roso?
Forget about me?
Ngelupain aku, Mbah?
How come he knows Rosso?
Eyang Darsono bisa tau Roso?
That's what I thought.
Lah, itu yang jadi kepikiran.
Because of that,
Sampe-sampe
I fell near the well.
kepeleset di sumur jadinya.
No need to think about it.
Udah, enggak usah dipikirin.
Let's go, come with me.
Ayo, ikut Simbah.
I will finish it later.
Ini nanti Simbah habiskan. Ya?
Where are we going?
Mau ke mana?
- Let's go. - Yes.
- Ayo. - Ya.
Let me help you.
Bisa?
Be careful, Grandma.
Hati-hati, Mbah.
Isn't this...
Ini...
Isn't this the road to Alas Kiwo?
Ini jalan menuju Alas Kiwo, hutan
The haunted forest, right?
yang katanya angker itu, 'kan, Mbah?
Your Grandpa Darsono was buried here, Tika.
Di sini makam eyangmu, Darsono, Tik.
He was buried along with the other victims.
Eyangmu dikubur bersama korban yang lainnya.
They were accused of being communist...
Mereka dibunuh dengan sadis
that's why they were brutally murdered.
karena dituduh komunis.
That's why this place is called Alas Kiwo, "The left hill".
Makanya, tempat ini disebut Alas Kiwo.
The hill where...
"Alas", hutan
people from the left-wing are buried.
tempat orang-orang kiri dikubur.
So,
Berarti,
this place is really haunted?
hutan ini memang angker, ya, Mbah?
They deliberately said...
Iya, sengaja
that this forest was haunted.
dianggap angker,
So, no one comes here to pray for their family.
biar penduduk enggak datang ke sini untuk mendoakan.
Your Grandpa was accused of being a communist...
Eyangmu dikomuniskan
by people who hated him.
sama mereka yang tidak suka sama dia.
That's cruel.
Jahat betul.
That's what happens...
Yah, begitulah.
when you're too fanatic with political parties.
Kalo terlalu fanatik dengan partai politik,
Innocent people become victims.
orang yang tidak berdosa jadi korban.
But, why did...
Tapi kenapa
Grandpa Darsono call me in your dream?
Eyang Darsono nyebut nama aku di mimpi Mbah?
He wants to
Dia mau menitipkan sesuatu
give you and Tika something.
sama kamu dan Tika.
What is it?
Titip apa, Mbah?
A very confidential and important thing that mustn't fall into anyone's hands.
Peninggalan yang tidak boleh jatuh ke tangan siapa pun.
One day, we had guests in our house.
Pada suatu sore, dateng beberapa tamu,
They said the President sent them.
bilangnya utusan Presiden.
Darsono, - I'm Major Bonar.
- Darsono. - Saya Mayor Bonar.
Captain Atmo.
Kapten Atmo.
Darsono.
Darsono.
Lieutnant Ismet.
Letnan Ismet.
We're here because...
Maksud kamu datang ke sini untuk...
Here, Sir.
Ini, Pak.
Mr. President appointed you.
Presiden sudah menunjuk Anda.
- Please, have a bite. - This is it.
- Wah, iya. - Silakan.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Please, dig in.
- Silakan, Pak. - Wah.
While eating Mangut,
Sambil mereka menyantap mangut,
they asked your Grandpa to join their project.
eyangmu diajak terlibat proyek besar.
You use your own technique to cook this!
Pasti cara masakmu berbeda.
No, I didn't. I cook like everyone else.
Ah, tidak, Pak. Sama kayak orang-orang, kok.
I understand why Mr. President chose you.
Tidak salah Pak Presiden memilih Anda, kalau begitu.
Along with 17 culturalists
Bersama 17 budayawan
and eight soldiers,
dan delapan perwira TNI...
your Grandpa went to see Mr. President,
...eyangmu menghadap Presiden
and he ordered them to...
dan diberikan mandat
collect 1945 food recipes...
mengumpulkan 1.945 resep
from every city in Indonesia.
makanan tiap-tiap daerah seluruh Indonesia
And that document is called Mustika Rasa
dan dinamakan Mustikarasa.
Tujuh belas Culturalists,
Tujuh belas budayawan,
eight soldiers,
delapan perwira.
1945 recipes.
Seribu sembilan ratus empat puluh lima resep.
Our independence day.
Tanggal kemerdekaan kita.
That's why Mustika Rasa...
Itulah kenapa Mustikarasa
became an important project that everyone protected.
jadi proyek penting yang diagungkan.
What about the other 945 recipes?
Sisa 945 resepnya gimana, Mbah?
That year, there was an uproar in our country,
Belom dibukukan. Belom sempat.
thus, they haven't been recorded yet.
Karena 'kan tahun itu terjadi huru-hara di negeri kita.
On 30 September 1965 in the morning,
30 September 1965 subuh,
there was a coup in Lubang Buaya...
di Lubang Buaya terjadi kudeta berdarah
that was planned by the Communist Parties...
yang didalangi partai komunis
which resulted in seven high-ranking soldiers dying.
dan menewaskan tujuh perwira angkatan darat.
Since then, the members of communist parties and those related,
Sejak saat itu, semua anggota PKI dan simpatisannya
were captured and murdered.
- ditangkap dan dibunuh. - Ya sudah, dimasukin...
Put it quickly. Leave it.
Duduk. Sudah, biar saya saja.
You should save yourself.
Kau selamatkan dirimu.
Alright, Sir.
Baik, Pak!
Where are you going Ismet?
Mau ke mana, Ismet?
Don't you dare take Mustika Rasa...
Jangan berani-berani kau bawa
out of this office.
Mustikarasa itu keluar ruangan!
Our country is in jeopardy.
Kamu harus segera pergi dari sini.
You have to save yourself.
Negara sedang kacau.
This is the key to our house.
Ini kunci rumah.
There's a safe at the back of the house...
Di sana ada bunker,
where I put all of our country's confidential documents.
tempat di mana aku menyimpan dokumen rahasia negara.
It's in the spices warehouse.
Di gudang rempah belakang rumah.
Protect these documents for me,
Tolong kau jaga dokumen ini.
and never give it to anyone.
Jangan berikan pada siapa pun.
I can entrust this to no one but you.
Tidak ada yang bisa kupercaya.
After Ketut Arsa arrives,
Nanti aku menyusul.
we will follow you.
Aku menunggu Ketut Arsa di sini.
That day was the last time I saw your Grandpa.
Itu kali terakhir Mbah lihat eyangmu.
Not long after,
Setelah itu,
I heard that...
Mbah dengar
your Grandpa was killed in Alas Kiwo.
eyangmu terbunuh di Alas Kiwo.
This warehouse
Dulu...
used to be Japan's weapons warehouse.
ini gudang persenjataan Jepang.
Then your Grandpa...
Lalu diubah sama eyangmu
turned it into his office.
jadi ruangan kerja.
Come in.
Ayo masuk.
Be careful, it's quite dark in here.
Gelap, ya? Pelan-pelan.
Let me turn on the lamp.
Aku hidupin dulu lampunya.
Careful, Grandma.
- Ini, Mbah. - Ya.
Come here.
Ke sini, Nak.
Here it is. Take out that briefcase under the table.
Ini, kamu ambil kopernya,
Here it is.
Ya, sini.
This is the rest of Mustika Rasa's recipes.
Ini sisa resep Mustikarasa.
Let me see.
Hitung, ya?
Both of you have to look after it.
Kalian harus menjaganya, ya?
Why does it have to be both of us?
Tika sama Roso?
Because both of you are the inheritors of Mustika Rasa.
Kalian adalah pewaris Mustikarasa.
But I'm not Grandpa Darsono's descendant, like Tika.
Tapi 'kan aku bukan anaknya Eyang Darsono kayak Tika, Mbah.
Here.
Ini.
The man in the middle was...
Yang di tengah
Ketut Arsa.
namanya Ketut Arsa.
He was my husband's best friend,
Dia sahabatnya Eyang Darsono.
a gastronome and a Chef.
Ahli gastronomi, sekaligus koki.
He was your biological Grandpa.
Dia eyangmu, Roso.
There is his blood in you.
Dia mewariskan darahnya di kamu.
That's why it didn't surprise me...
Jadi, Mbah enggak heran
when you become a wonderful chef.
kalo sekarang kamu jadi koki hebat.
He had the same fate as Grandpa Darsono.
Yah, nasibnya sama dengan Eyang Darsono.
He was killed and left two daughters behind.
Dia meninggalkan dua orang anak, masih kecil.
And one of them is your mom.
Ya, salah satunya ibumu.
Grandma.
Mbah,
Are these the 17 Mustika Rasa culturalists?
di tujuh belas budayawan Mustikarasa,
Is this him, Grandma?
ini beliau, Mbah?
Along with Ir. Soekarno?
Barengan sama Bung Karno?
Deep down I know my mother didn't abandon me.
Aku emang dari dulu yakin aku bukan anak buangan.
Your mom is Tika's mother's best friend,
Simbah kenal ibumu, Roso.
so, I know her.
Dia 'kan sahabat ibunya Tika.
Grandma.
- Mbah. - Hmm?
Is this my mother?
Ini Ibu?
That's right.
Oh, iya, bener.
This is your mom,
Ini ibumu.
and this is Evi, Rosso's mother.
Ini Evi, ibunya Roso.
She looks like my adopted mother, Eva.
Mirip sama Mama Eva.
Many people mistake them for twins.
Banyak orang bilang mereka kembar.
Evi is like your Grandpa,
Kalo Evi,
she has strong principles.
itu karakter eyangmu. Prinsipnya kuat.
Where are they now?
Tapi mereka sekarang ada di mana, Mbah?
They are on the missing people list.
Mereka masuk daftar orang hilang.
THE REASONS FOR THE CLOSURE OF PRODUCTION ARE NAMED!
...meninggalkan
IS THIS RELATED TO THE BANKRUPTCY OF THE COMPANY?
kesedihan mendalam...
Until today,
Tapi sampe hari ini
we don't know where they are.
belum ditemukan.
Without me realizing it...
Tanpa Simbah sadari,
I lost Ratih because of Jakarta's political situation.
situasi politik Jakarta membuat Simbah kehilangan Ratih.
Mother...
Ibu,
We're in danger.
saya dan kawan-kawan dalam bahaya.
I need to run and hide.
Saya harus lari.
Please take care of Tika.
Titip Tika dulu, ya, Bu.
I'll pick her up
Kalo sudah aman,
once the situation is safe.
Ratih akan ambil kembali.
I'm sorry.
Maafkan Ratih, ya, Bu.
Two days later,
Dua hari kemudian,
Evi gave you to Grandpa Darmo.
Evi menitipkan kamu, Roso, ke Darmo.
She followed Ratih.
Rupanya dia menyusul Ratih.
She said that...
Evi menitipkan pesan kalo suatu saat nanti,
later on, either she or her sister...
Roso akan diambil kembali
will pick Rosso up.
oleh dirinya atau adiknya.
Please take care of this legacy.
Tolong jaga warisan ini, ya?
Never hand this to other people.
Jangan diserahkan ke orang lain.
Especially these two soldiers.
Apalagi sama ini, nih. Kepada dua perwira ini.
This is a stress ball from my doctor.
Ini semacam bola stres dari dokter aku.
My stress-reliever.
Temen aku kalo lagi stres.
I didn't expect that...
Aku enggak nyangka
my healing would be like this.
rencana pemulihan aku jadi kayak gini.
At least,
Ya, seenggaknya,
now you know where you come from.
sekarang kamu jadi tau siapa dirimu sebenernya.
My taste buds are healed.
Lidah aku sembuh,
I've overcome my trauma.
trauma aku sama bumbu hilang...
But the most important thing,
Dan yang paling penting...
I have my friend back.
aku dapet temen aku lagi.
So, you don't need these now?
Berarti sekarang udah enggak butuh ini, ya?
And what's next?
Terus sekarang gimana?
I don't know.
Aku enggak tau, Tik.
You wouldn't be here if you hadn't lost your taste buds.
Kalo lidahmu enggak mati rasa juga paling kamu enggak ada di sini.
That's true.
Iya.
Successfully ran my food test...
- Pasti uji makanan udah sukses. - Hmm.
and had a restaurant in Gragnano.
Mungkin sekarang aku udah jalanin restoran di Gragnano.
Why don't you do it now?
Kenapa enggak kamu kejar sekarang?
Actually, that's my father's dream.
Itu tuh sebetulnya impian papa aku.
It's his childhood dream...
Dia tuh dari kecil punya impian
to have a restaurant in his hometown.
buka restoran di kota kelahirannya.
When he died,
Dan pada saat beliau meninggal...
I promised him...
Aku udah janji sama dia,
I'd make his dream come true.
akan aku buka restoran itu.
That's how it is.
Gitu.
You can make it happen.
Aku yakin, kok,
I'm sure of it.
kamu bisa ngewujudin itu.
It's not that easy.
Ya, enggak segampang itu, Tik.
Now I know who I am.
Apalagi sekarang aku udah tau asal-usul aku.
Who my parents are, my Grandpa.
Orang tua kandung aku, kakek aku.
Your life is not here, Rosso.
Hidupmu bukan di sini, Ros.
I couldn't leave you behind,
Aku juga enggak mungkin ninggalin kamu, Tik,
especially with that huge bequest!
dengan warisan segede itu.
It shouldn't be your concern, don't you think?
Kamu jangan jadi terbebani karena itu, enggak, sih?
How can I possibly carry out my Father's dream in peace?
Mau gimana, Tik? Aku enggak mungkin bisa jalanin impian papa aku dengan tenang.
How can I?
Enggak mungkin.
It won't be possible, unless...
Kecuali mungkin...
Unless I accompany you?
Kecuali aku ikut kamu?
I can't do that.
Enggak bisa.
- Now way. I can't do that. - Tika.
- Enggak bisa. - Tik.
Why?
- Kenapa enggak bisa? - Lho?
Why can't you?
Kenapa enggak bisa?
Can't you see it?
Roso, kamu ngerti, enggak, sih?
My life is here.
Hidupku di sini.
I can't leave Grandma behind.
Aku enggak mungkin ninggalin Simbah.
- I didn't ask you to leave her. - Then?
- Aku enggak nyuruh kamu ninggalin Mbah. - Terus?
Then what?
Terus?
- Maybe I'll move... - No.
- Ya, mungkin aku yang... - Enggak.
You'll move?
Kamu yang mau tinggal di sini?
You'll move here permanently?
Mau tinggal di sini permanen?
Is it wrong that I wanna stay with you?
Emang salah, aku mau sama kamu?
I will leave everything behind.
Aku tinggalin semuanya.
You're the one who said it.
Kamu yang bilang, 'kan?
You said it is love.
Cinta.
Yes, Gareng?
Ada apa, Mas Gareng?
What?
Apa?
By whom?
Siapa?
They seem scary.
- Serem... - Serem.
Sis.
Mbakyu.
Tarjo forced us to open because there's a VIP.
Tarjo maksa suruh buka warung. Katanya ada orang penting.
Who are they?
Mereka siapa?
I don't know, I've never seen them.
Enggak tau! Aku enggak pernah lihat!
Mr. Broto.
Pak Broto.
Where have you been?
Dari mana aja kamu?
I've been waiting for the food tasting
Aku tunggu uji menu kamu,
but you're nowhere to be seen.
kok malah hilang?
How could you know that I'm here?
Pak Broto kok bisa tau kita ada di sini?
This restaurant...
Warungmu itu
went viral.
viral.
The show is talking about your specialty.
Acaranya tentang makanan andalan kalian.
Mangut.
Mangut.
So, if it possible...
Jadi, kalo tidak keberatan,
can I try the Mangut?
apakah saya boleh mencicipi mangut itu?
I apologize in advance.
Mohon maaf sebelumnya, Pak.
I'm Tika.
- Saya Tika. - Oh, iya.
Subroto, you can call me Broto.
Saya Subroto. Panggil aja Broto.
Our restaurant is closed for today,
Kebetulan warung kami sedang tutup, Pak.
you can come back tomorrow.
Baru masak lagi besok.
I'll pay extra...
Saya akan bayar lebih
so you can buy all the ingredients that you need.
supaya kalian masih bisa cari bahan-bahan makanan itu.
Here's the money.
Nih, ya.
Please take it.
Silakan.
So, can I try the Mangut?
Bisa, 'kan?
We have all the ingredients,
Bahan-bahannya ada di belakang, kok, Pak.
we will cook it for you.
- Aku masakkan. - Baik.
- You have all the ingredients, right? - Yes, we do have it all.
- Bisa dimasakin. Ya, masih banyak. Ya. - Masih ada, 'kan, bahannya?
Come on Tika, let's cook.
- Ya. - Masih ada.
Miss.
Mbak.
Please...
Tolong, dong,
cook the Mangut for me.
masakin buat saya.
Please?
Bisa?
We got a lot of money, Gareng.
Duit gede ini, Reng.
Careful.
Kerjain, Reng.
How much will I get?
Aku berapa?
I'll give you ten percent as usual.
Sepuluh persen, kayak biasa.
Eleven percent.
Sebelas!
I'll give you 15%.
Lima belas aku kasih!
That's good!
Nah, gas!
Let's start cooking!
Ayo masak!
- Help me, Sister! - What is it?
- Mbakyu, tolong itu, Mbakyu! - Apa?
- The catfish! - Okay, I'll help you.
- Lele. - Aku belikan.
I'd like to...
Saya
apologize...
minta maaf
on behalf of my daughter.
atas kelakuan
And as I offer my apologies,
Dan tanda maaf saya itu,
I'll help you and invest...
saya akan berinvestasi
in your restaurant in Italy.
di restoran kamu yang di Italia itu.
You can tell me,
Tinggal kamu bilang sama saya.
when and where you wanna build it.
Kapan, dan di mana lokasinya.
We will build it together.
Nanti kita bangun bersama.
Okay?
Oke?
May I think about it first?
Boleh saya pikir-pikir dulu?
The smell is very appetizing.
Wah, luar biasa aromanya.
Give me the plate.
Piring...
Let's eat!
Makan! Semuanya.
Woah!
Waduh!
This is so delicious!
Nikmat luar biasa.
The last time I at this kind of incredible Mangut...
Terakhir kali aku makan mangut istimewa ini,
was 55 years ago.
lima puluh lima tahun yang lalu.
Even my tongue couldn't forget the taste of it.
Bayangkan. Masih terasa di lidah.
I might be wrong but...
Dan kalo aku boleh sok tau, ya,
you cook...
kamu masak mangut ini
the Mangut by...
pasti dengan cara
curing the fish with candlenut wood.
pengasapan kayu kemiri.
Do you know about curing the fish with candlenut wood?
Bapak tau pengasapan kayu kemiri?
Of course, I know.
Hebat, 'kan?
Aren't I amazing?
Ya, tau.
You're incredible, Tika.
Kamu luar biasa, Tika.
The cooking technique
Ini teknik memasak
that you're using is very unique.
yang khas.
Everyone should know the special food that...
Masakan dan teknik yang khas ini
is made by this unique technique.
harus menyebar ke mana-mana.
So, if you want to expand this restaurant,
Jadi, kalo kamu mau mengembangkan warung ini,
please, do not hesitate...
kamu jangan ragu-ragu.
to call me.
Hubungi saya. Ya?
Give me that. Here is my name card.
Cepet. Nah, ini kartu nama saya.
Here.
Oke? Ya?
Your restaurant is very special...
Seperti warungmu ini
and every person in Indonesia has to know.
dengan keistimewaannya, harus menyebar di seluruh Nusantara.
Mr. Broto knows about curing with candlenut wood.
Pak Broto tadi bilang soal pengasapan kayu kemiri.
How come he knows that?
Tau dari mana dia soal itu?
He's one of the President's advisors,
Pak Broto itu penasihat Presiden
who's concerned about Indonesian food.
yang perhatian soal pangan-pangan Indonesia, jadi...
It's a no-brainer that he knows a lot about that.
Ya, enggak heran kalo dia emang tau soal hal-hal kayak gitu.
My Grandpa made that curing method...
Pengasapan kayu kemiri
only for the family.
diciptakan sama Eyang Darsono hanya untuk keluarga.
There's no way he knows that.
Dia enggak mungkin tau.
I'm sure he knows my Grandpa.
Aku yakin Pak Broto kenal sama Eyang Darsono.
What if...
Atau jangan-jangan...
he is one of the soldiers in that photo?
dia salah satu perwira yang ada di foto itu?
Let's see.
Coba.
No one resembles him,
Enggak ada yang mirip.
I don't think he was one of them.
Enggak mungkin kayaknya.
Here, you can check it thoroughly.
Coba kamu cek.
I will drive.
Aku bawa, ya.
We need to talk to Grandma about Mr. Broto.
Kita harus bicara sama Simbah soal Pak Broto.
I'll go home first.
Yuk, pulang!
Okay, be careful.
- Ya, hati-hati! - Ya!
May peace be upon you.
Assalamualaikum.
Grandma?
Mbah?
Mrs. Sunarti suffered from anoxia brain injury...
Ibu Sunarti mengalami cedera otak anoksik
because of the lack of oxygen in her brain.
karena kurangnya oksigen ke otak.
This can occur in situations like stroke,
Ini dapat terjadi dalam situasi strok,
traumatic incident,
serangan traumatis,
choking out or overdose.
tersedak, atau overdosis.
We'll try our best.
Kami akan berbuat sebaik mungkin.
Thank you.
Makasih, ya, Dok.
Grandma.
Mbah.
Please wake up, Grandma.
Bangun, Mbah.
Let's eat the spaghetti that Rosso made again.
Nanti kita makan spagetinya Roso lagi.
Let's...
Nanti kita...
visit Grandpa Darsono's grave together again.
nyekar Eyang ke makamnya lagi.
I have a lot of questions regarding Mustika Rasa.
Aku punya pertanyaan tentang Mustikarasa.
You have to answer them all.
Mbah harus jawab.
Grandma, please wake up.
Bangun, Mbah.
So, your Grandma already...
Jadi, mbahmu udah cerita, ya,
told you about the recipe documents?
soal dokumen resep itu?
Why can't you...
Mbakyu...
give that up?
Kamu kok enggak kapok-kapok?
Those cursed documents...
Mengorbankan orang lain,
already have...
gara-gara dokumen
many casualties.
terkutuk itu.
Why did you say that, Grandpa?
Mbah Darmo kok ngomongnya kayak gitu?
Mustika Rasa is a curse, Tika.
Mustikarasa itu kutukan, Tika.
It is a curse for my family,
Buat keluargaku,
my brother,
buat kakang masku,
your Grandma and her kids.
simbahmu, dan anak-anaknya.
Including your mother.
Termasuk ibumu.
Everyone becomes the victims.
Semua jadi korban.
The first time I heard about Mustika Rasa...
Waktu Mbah pertama kali tau tentang Mustikarasa
a project that my brother was proud of,
yang dibangga-banggakan Kangmas Darsono,
I was only 12 years old.
umurku baru 12 tahun.
Darsono and your Grandpa, Ketut Arsa...
Darsono dan eyangmu, Ketut Arsa,
were talking very seriously.
terlibat dalam percakapan serius.
The President asked them to hide several numbers that...
Presiden menugaskan mereka menyelipkan angka-angka yang
I didn't know what it was for.
Simbah enggak ngerti.
But, it turns out...
Tapi ternyata,
that those numbers are coordinates of a treasure location
angka-angka itu adalah koordinat sebuah lokasi harta karun
that is hidden randomly on
yang diselipkan ke dalam 1.945 lembar dokumen Mustikarasa
the rest of the 945 pages of Mustika Rasa.
secara acak.
Your Grandpa, Ressa,
Dan eyangmu, Ressa,
he wasn't sure about this action,
meragukan tindakan ini dan menanyakan,
he thinks that those numbers should be placed in a safer place.
mengapa angka-angka berharga ini tidak disimpan di tempat lebih aman saja?
But my brother, Darsono, said that
Tapi kangmasku, Darsono, ngotot
there will be turmoil on the military base.
kalau akan terjadi kekacauan di kalangan militer,
Thus, these maps should be put in unexpected places.
sehingga peta ini harus disimpan di tempat yang tidak terduga.
This is a conspiracy, Darsono.
Konspirasi ini, Dar!
This is a duty from our country, Ketut.
Tut! Ini tugas negara, Tut.
A treasure map?
Peta harta karun?
That's right.
Iya.
The location of the biggest mine in the world.
Itu lokasi tambang terbesar di dunia.
Bigger than the gold mine in Mimika, Central Papua.
Lebih besar dari tambang emas yang ada di Mimika, Papua Barat.
If we're talking about the value, how much would it be?
Memangnya kalau harta itu dinilaikan, sebesar apa, Mbah?
If the gold mine was found,
Kalau letak tambang itu ditemukan,
Indonesia would be the richest country in the world.
Indonesia akan menjadi negara paling kaya di dunia.
That's why everyone is looking for that document.
Pantes dokumen itu banyak yang cari.
People who have those documents...
Semua orang yang memegang dokumen itu
will get cursed, including both of you.
akan kena kutukan, termasuk kalian.
Then, what should we do?
Terus, kita harus gimana, Mbah?
I think...
Yah...
just give it back to the government.
Kembalikan saja ke negara.
You could give it to him,
Dia itu 'kan penasihat Presiden.
as he's one of the President's advisors.
Kembalikan saja ke dia.
That's true.
Iya, Tik.
I think we should give him the documents. Don't you agree?
Kita balikin aja ke dia. Gimana?
No.
Enggak.
I can't make a decision...
Aku enggak bisa bikin keputusan
before discussing it with Grandma first.
sebelom dapet persetujuan dari Simbah.
Look at your Grandma's condition, Tika.
Lihat saja bagaimana kondisi simbahmu, Tika.
- Let's eat first. - Yes.
Makan dulu, yuk.
Delicious.
Enak.
In my opinion,
- Kalo menurut aku, ya, Tik... - Hmm?
only the government has the right to keep the document.
Cuma negara yang berhak megang dokumen itu.
The responsibility is too extensive,
Soalnya nilainya terlalu besar.
don't you think so?
Iya, enggak, sih?
But,
Tapi...
if it's that massive...
Kalo memang nilainya sebesar itu...
why did the President entrust it to Grandpa?
kenapa dulu Presiden ngasihnya ke Eyang?
Why didn't he give it to Bonar or Atmo?
Kenapa enggak ke Bonar atau ke Atmo?
Rosso!
Ros!
Dinda.
Din.
I... I didn't come here because Papa asked me to.
A... Aku ke sini enggak disuruh Papa.
Can we go inside to talk?
Boleh, enggak, kita ngobrol di dalem?
Rosso.
Roso.
I'll go to the kitchen for a bit.
Aku mau ke dapur dulu, ya.
I'm here to prevent things before it's too late.
Aku dateng ke sini sebelum semuanya terlambat.
You're a good man, Ressa.
Kamu laki-laki naik, Res.
I now realize that I was stupid
Aku sadar kalo aku bodoh.
and got fooled by Papa and Alex.
Bisa dibego-begoin ama Papa, ama Alex.
If you're here because of that incident, I'm alr...
Kalo kamu ke sini cuma mau ngomongin soal peristiwa itu, aku udah...
Please, listen to me first, Ressa.
Dengerin aku dulu, Res. Tolong.
Alright.
Ya udah.
Papa already planned this.
Ini semua tuh skenario Papa.
Alex and I were having an affair,
Kita emang selingkuh,
but I never gave him an access card.
tapi aku enggak pernah ngasih kartu aksesnya ke dia.
Papa is the one who gave it to him.
Papa yang ngasih, Res.
Dinda...
Din...
It's enough, Din. Please.
Udah, ya? Tolong.
I'm sorry Ressa.
Aku minta maaf, Res.
Please, stop having contact with my Dad.
Aku mohon untuk kamu stop berhubungan sama Papa.
What do you mean?
Maksud kamu apa, sih?
Papa must have tried to convince you...
Papa pasti udah bujuk kamu, 'kan?
about the restaurant in Gragnano, right?
Soal restoran yang di Gragnano,
He also offered Tika to expand her restaurant.
dan juga udah nawarin Tika untuk mengembangkan warung makannya.
It is all his ploy, Ressa.
Itu semua cuma topeng, Res.
A ploy to snatch Mustika Rasa from you and Tika.
Topeng Papa untuk ngerebut Mustikarasa dari kamu sama Tika.
How do you know about Mustika Rasa?
Kamu tau dari mana soal Mustikarasa?
Papa is obsessed with Mustika Rasa.
Mustikarasa itu obsesi Papa.
I heard that...
Saya mendengar
the President...
pengumuman Presiden
is banning the import of rice.
tentang pelarangan impor beras.
That policy is interrupting our business.
Ini sangat mengganggu bisnis kita.
Finding...
Dan jalan satu-satunya,
the rest of Mustika Rasa is our only way.
kita harus cepat mendapatkan sisa dokumen Mustikarasa ini,
Because inside those documents,
karena di balik dokumen itu,
there's a treasure map...
ada peta harta karun
that is worth an incalculable amount.
yang nilainya begitu besar dan luar biasa.
Understand?
Paham?
Yes, Sir.
Siap, Pak!
We'll look for it.
Kita cari.
Papa knows both of you are related
Papa tau kalo Mustikarasa tuh terhubung
to Mustika Rasa because of your Mangut.
sama kalian karena mangutmu.
Who's your father?
Papamu sebenernya siapa, sih?
He's Major Bonar,
Mayor Bonar.
isn't he?
Bener, enggak?
He's not.
Bukan.
I'm Captain Atmojo.
Saya Kapten Atmojo.
Subroto Sastro Atmojo.
Subroto Sastro Atmojo.
Then, I changed it into...
Lalu kuganti
Subroto Mangku Projo.
jadi Subroto Mangkuprojo.
That's the name you're familiar with, right?
Itu, 'kan, nama yang kalian kenal?
Don't you dare...
Jangan berani-berani kau bawa
bring Mustika Rasa out of this office.
Mustikarasa itu keluar ruangan.
Ismet.
Ismet.
Hurry up! We have to go out now.
Ayo cepat. Harus pergi.
- What about the money, Sir? - It's in the car.
- Uangnya, Pak? - Sudah saya siapkan di mobil.
- Quick. - Alright, Sir.
- Ayo cepet. Cepet. - Baik, Pak.
Bastard!
Bajingan!
Where's the rest?
Kok cuma segini?
Darsono, you bastard!
Sialan kamu, Darsono!
Papa!
Papa.
Thank you Dinda...
Dinda, terima kasih, ya.
for doing your part very well.
Kamu telah bekerja dengan baik.
You said you're not here because your Papa asked you.
Kamu bilang ke sini bukan karena disuruh sama papamu.
I'm not!
Memang bukan.
Liar!
Bohong!
Take her to the car.
Bawa ke mobil.
Papa!
Pa!
Let me go!
Pa, suruh lepasin, Pa!
Ressa, Tika, run!
Ressa, Tika, lari! Pa!
Let me go, Papa.
Pa, lepasin, Pa!
Slut's son, where are you going?
Anak pelacur mau ke mana?
Run, Tika!
Tika, lari!
Get him.
Goblok!
Rosso!
Roso!
Bastard! I'll kill you!
Bangsat! Diam kamu!
Tarjo!
Tarjo!
Shut up, Tika!
Kamu diem, Tik! Tenang!
Narti, Narti.
Narti...
You're very clever...
Betapa cerdiknya kamu
at keeping Darsono's stuff.
menyimpan peninggalan-peninggalan Darsono.
The documents that you're looking for...
Dokumen yang Bapak cari
are buried with my Grandpa in Alas Kiwo.
terkubur di Alas Kiwo bersama jasad Eyang Darsono.
You can't fool me, I know it's not true.
Oh, ya? Tapi aku punya petunjuk lain.
I dug up the grave in Alas Kiwo, Tika.
Aku dari kuburan Alas Kiwo, Tik.
The deeper I dug,
Sudah kugali sedalam-dalamnya,
I found nothing other than the bones of Communist Party members.
yang kutemukan cuma tulang belulang PKI.
There's no Mustika Rasa document.
Enggak ada dokumen Mustikarasa.
How much did he pay you?
Kamu dibayar berapa?
To the point that you betray your own family?
Sampai tega
I want to save our family, Tika!
Aku justru ingin menyelamatkan keluarga kita, Tika.
Especially you and your Grandma.
Terutama kamu dan Simbah.
Mustika Rasa is cursed.
Dokumen Mustikarasa itu terkutuk.
It's better to give it to Mr. Broto.
Sebaiknya kamu berikan kepada Pak Broto.
No way!
Enggak sudi!
What?
Paman!
Too much drama.
Terlalu banyak drama!
Broto, you bastard!
Bangsat kamu, Broto!
Shut up!
Diam!
Evil General!
Jenderal iblis!
I'll kill your boyfriend...
Kalau kamu tetap bungkam,
if you keep silent.
aku akan menghancurkan pacarmu ini!
Where did you hide it?
Di mana?
Where?
Di mana kau simpan?
Where did you hide that document?
Bilang di mana kamu meletakkan dokumen itu!
I'll count to three,
Aku hitung sampai tiga.
then I'll blow your boyfriend's head off.
Aku akan pecahkan kepala pacarmu!
One!
Satu!
- Two! - Don't!
- Dua! - Jangan...
- Thre... - The spices store room!
- Ti... - Gudang rempah!
What?
Apa?
The spices store room.
Gudang rempah.
The spices store room!
Gudang rempah!
Thank you!
Terima kasih.
Rosso!
Roso!
There's no need to be dramatic, just give it to us!
Enggak usah kayak sinetron! Ayo cepet, buruan!
Come on!
Cepetan!
Where is it?
Di mana?
Why are you standing still? Hurry up!
Ayo, jangan diam saja.
Tika!
Tik!
Where's that document?
Di mana kamu simpan dokumen itu?
Do not prolong it!
Jangan ulur waktu!
I'll kill your boyfriend if you keep slowing us down!
Main-main, aku bunuh pacarmu!
Lead us, Tika!
Tika, tunjukin.
Why did you open that jar?
Kok malah buka toples ini, sih? Tik...
Where is it exactly?
Yang benar! Di mana?
Darsono, Darsono!
Darsono...
Lead the way, Tika!
Tika, ayo tunjukin jalannya.
Darsono, what a clever man!
Memang cerdik kamu!
Wow.
Wah.
It's just like this.
Seperti ini.
Hurry up!
Ayo cepet!
Where?
Di mana?
What a slow person!
Lama!
Search it!
Cari!
Got it?
Di mana?
Where do you keep the documents?
Di mana kamu simpan dokumennya?
Where is it?
Di mana?
Wait, Sir.
Sebentar, Bos.
Here it is!
Ini, Pak Bos.
Open it up!
Buka...
You Moron!
Goblok!
Give it to her! She knows the code!
Dia yang ngerti kodenya! Kasih ke dia!
Open it!
Buka.
Amazing.
Luar biasa.
Darsono,
Darsono!
you're a genius!
Genius kamu! Genius!
Katherine, keep it!
Jangan ada yang ilang! Simpen!
Yes, Sir.
Siap, Pak.
Sir. Is that all, Sir?
Pak Bos. Harta karunnya cuma itu?
Where's the gold?
Enggak ada emasnya?
Alex!
Alex!
Tika!
Tika!
Pa, please, Pa.
Pa, tolong, Pa.
Dinda!
Dinda!
Do not move!
Jangan bergerak!
Put down your gun!
Turunkan senjata!
Tika, wake up!
Tik!
Wake up, Tika!
Tik, bangun, Tik.
Tika!
Tika!
Good morning, Sir.
Selamat pagi, Bapak.
Good morning, Katherine.
Selamat pagi, Cath.
These are the Mustika Rasa documents.
Ini dokumen Mustikarasa, Pak.
Thank you.
Terima kasih.
Yes, Sir. Please, I'll excuse myself.
Siap, mohon izin, Pak.
Ah, right!
Oh, iya.
Please inform Ressa that...
Sampaikan kepada Ressa,
Mr. President will come
bahwa Pak Presiden akan datang secara langsung
to his restaurant's grand opening to show his gratitude since...
di pembukaan restorannya untuk mengucapkan terima kasih atas
he returned these very important and confidential documents.
pengembalian harta negara yang sangat penting ini.
Yes, Sir.
Siap.
I'll inform them.
Akan saya sampaikan.
Please excuse me.
Mohon izin, Pak.
Go ahead.
Silakan.
Here it is...
Inilah...
the Indonesian fusion pasta.
spageti Nusantara.
Please enjoy it.
Selamat menikmati.
Please eat.
Silakan!
Woah...
Sini.
- Are you okay, Grandma? - I'm fine.
- Simbah udah makannya? - Udah.
Do you feel uncomfortable?
- Enggak mau yang lain? - Enggak ada.
Here it is, Grandma.
Silakan, Mbah.
Try it.
Silakan.
I want to try it.
Ini harus aku coba.
Is there any left?
Aku mau ke sana dulu. Masih ada, 'kan?
Yes.
Ya.
- There is a lot more. - Okay.
- Masih banyak. - Oke.
I can see from the presentation that it will taste good.
Ini kalo lihat penampilannya, udah oke.
Let me try it.
Aku coba, ya.
It is delicious!
Enak.
Thank you, Grandma.
Terima kasih, Mbah.
Both of you deserve this.
Kalian memang sudah sepantasnya mendapatkan hadiah ini.
Take good care of it, okay?
Kalian harus menjaganya, ya.
Of course, Grandma.
Iya, Mbah.
Tika, Ressa.
Mbak Tika, Mas Ressa.
Mr. President is very sorry that he couldn't attend...
Mohon maaf, Pak Presiden izin harus ke Papua
because he has to go to Papua to inaugurate the toll road.
karena harus meresmikan jalan tol.
But he sends you a video.
Tapi beliau menitip pesan lewat video.
On behalf of this country,
Atas nama negara,
I'd like to thank...
saya mengucapkan terima kasih banyak
Chef Ressa and Chef Tika,
untuk Chef Ressa, Chef Tika
who were brave enough to protect
atas keberaniannya menyelamatkan
our country's confidential documents.
dokumen negara.
Here's your drink, Sir.
Minumnya, Pak.
Sir, may I come to the Rahasia Rasa cafe?
Izin bertanya, apakah saya bisa merapat ke Kafe Rahasia Rasa segera?